A Guide to the William Bradford Alwood Collection, 1854-1927
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William Bradford Alwood Collection, 1854-1927
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1960-003
5 boxes and 6 oversized folders; 1.9 cu. ft.
Professor of horticulture, entomology, and mycology at Virginia Tech (1891-1904); fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science. Papers include research papers, theses, brochures, and notebooks on such subjects as cider, wine making, grapes, and pellagra.
William B. Alwood
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The William Bradford Alwood Papers were acquired by the library prior to 1960. An addition to the collection was donated to Special Collections in 2007.
Biographical Information
William Bradford Alwood was born August 11, 1859 in Delta, Ohio. He attended Ohio State University and George Washington University. He also received training at the Royal Pomology School in Germany, and the Pasteur Institute in France. Alwood served as the Vice-Director of the Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station from 1888 to 1904. During this time he served as Professor of Horticulture, Entomology, and Mycology at the Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
After leaving VPI in 1904, Alwood moved to Charlottesville where he established an enological laboratory which was later incorporated into the USDA Bureau of Chemistry; he was named Chief of Enological Investigations. He continued his relationship with VPI by donating several books and papers to the library and kept in touch with old colleagues. He was awarded a certificate of merit by VPI in 1923. Alwood died April 13, 1946.
Scope and Content
The collection mainly consists of pamphlets and papers relating to various subjects including wine making, apples, pears, grapes, bacteriology, and fungi. Research papers and theses are also present in the collection. The collection also included 15 notebooks containing notes relating to Alwood's research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series: Series I which consists of pamphlet files is arranged alphabetically by subject, Series II which is composed of research papers and theses is arranged in chronological order and with series III, the research notebooks, arranged in numerical order.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; History of Food and Drink; Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College; Virginia Agriculutral and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute
Contents List
- Pamphlet files, 1894-1927
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Alcoholometer (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Apple (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Apple (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Bacteriology - Illustrations (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Black rot; Champagne (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Cider (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Cream of Tartar - Ginseng (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Grapes (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Histology - Pears (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Pellagra - Tartaric Acid (Box-folder 1:11)
  - USDA Bureau of Chemistry - Enological Lab (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Vinegar (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Wine and Winemaking (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Wine and Winemaking - Report on fermentation and composition of Catawba wines, 1913 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Wine and Winemaking - Report on fermentation and composition of Norton wines, 1914 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Wine and Winemaking - Report on fermentation and composition of Clinton, Cynthiana, Montefiore, and Schraidtes wines, 1915 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Wine - Analyses, Tables (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Reprints, 1894-1915 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Bacteriology-Illustrations; Cider; Cream of Tartar (Oversize 1)
  - Grapes (Oversize 2)
  - Insects - Classification; USDA Bureau of Chemistry, Enological Laboratory (Oversize 3)
  - Wines and Winemaking - Fermentation and compostion of Catawba wines, 1913 (Oversize 4)
  - Wine and Winemaking - Report on fermentation and composition of Norton wines, 1914 (Oversize 5)
  - Wine and Winemaking - Report on fermentation and composition of Clinton, Cynthiana, Montefiore, and Schraidtes wines, 1915 (Oversize 6)
- Research papers and Theses, 1854-1914
  - Bitter Rot - Research and Correspondence, 1854-1903 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Bitter Rot - Research and Correspondence, 1854-1903 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Project Outlines, 1908-1914 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Theses - Early records, 1910 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Mycology, 1910-1914 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Cedar Rust Research, 1914 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Plant Disease Survey, 1914 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Spray Injury, 1914 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Frog-eye Leaf Spot, 1914 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Research Notebooks, 1888-1912
  - Laboratory Notes, 1888 (Box-notebook 4:1)
  - Notes - U.S. Enological Station, Sandusky, Ohio, 1910 (Box-notebook 4:2)
  - Cellar Book No. 1, 1907-1908 (Box-notebook 4:3)
  - Cellar Book No. 2, 1908-1909 (Box-notebook 4:4)
  - Cellar Book, Sandusky, 1911 (Box-notebook 4:5)
  - Monometer Tests, 1908 (Box-notebook 4:6)
  - Notes - Experimental tests on methods, 1909 (Box-notebook 4:7)
  - Apples (Box-notebook 5:8)
  - Commercial Wines, 1911 (Box-notebook 5:9)
  - Samples, Lab entry number, 1911 (Box-notebook 5:10)
  - Weight Book, 1911-1912 (Box-notebook 5:11)
  - Current Lab Notes, 1907 (Box-notebook 5:12)
  - Analyses, 1911 (Box-notebook 5:13)
  - Notes on Analysis, 1911 (Box-notebook 5:14)
  - [No Title], 1907 (Box-notebook 5:15)
  - Yeast record, 1909 (Box-notebook 5:16)